Guide to the Rice University Welfare Committee records, 1961-1972 UA 177
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Welfare Committee records
1961-1972
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 177
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The collection consists of the notes, correspondence, and minutes of the Committee on University Welfare, formed in 1961. It served as a grievance committee until 1971 when the committee disbanded and its functions were taken over by the newly organized Faculty Council and the University Council.
Biographical / Historical
The University Welfare Committee, elected in October 1962 by the faculty, met for the first time Nov. 26, 1962. President Pitzer had asked for this committee to consider all matters not dealt with by other committees. Topics were to be initiated within or outside the committee. The members would then examine and criticize issues brought before them and report their findings to President Pitzer and the faculty. The committee functioned somewhat as a grievance committee and dealt with a diverse number of matters over the years which ranged from inadequate lighting on campus, faculty pension plans and tenure, to student-faculty-administration relationships. It was out of the latter issue that in May 1971 a University Council was formed with representatives from the student body, the faculty, and the administration. It functioned as the primary adviser to the president on policy decisions and matters affecting the operation of the University. At the same time a Faculty Council was formed, constituted partly by faculty members of the University Council. The Faculty Council assumed all the duties of the Committee on University Welfare, which disbanded in 1971. (J. McDermott, 5/5/82)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of notes, correspondence, and minutes drawn from several sources, primarily President Pitzer's Papers, Acting President Vandiver and President Hackerman's Papers. Some were from an unknown source, perhaps the early committee chairmen. There was no cohesive structure to the files and so they were interfiled chronologically. This method shows, in most cases, issues brought before the committee and the process of their resolution from start to finish.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transfered May, 1982 from Rice University Presidents' Papers (Pitzer, Hackerman)
Index Terms
Subjects
Faculty; Education, Higher -- Texas; Universities and colleges
Document Types
letters (correspondence); minutes (administrative records); notes
Places
Rice University
Subjects (Persons)
Pitzer, Kenneth S. (Kenneth Sanborn)
- Series I: 1960s, 209611
  - Notes, Correspondence 1961-1962, 209614 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1962-1963, 209615 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1963-1964, 209616 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1964-1965, 209617 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1964-1965, 209618 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1965-1966, 209619 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1966-1967, 209620 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1967-1968, 209621 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1968-1969, 209622 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1969-1970, 209625 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Series II: 1970s, 209612
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1970-71, 209626 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, Notes, Correspondence 1971-1972, 209627 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Undated Material, 209628 (Box 2, Folder 7)